<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Computational Intelligence Library]]></title>
  <link href="http://cilib.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cilib.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-12-19T10:35:45+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://cilib.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[CIRG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CIlib 0.7.5 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/075-release/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/075-release</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 0.7.5 release of CIlib has been staged. The release consists of many changes from
various contributors. We would like to thank everyone for the contributions to this
release. What follows are the main highlights for the 0.7.5 release.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Change Log</h3>

<p>Numerous changes have been included into the release, but the most notable are listed here:</p>

<ul>
<li>New clustering implementation (for PSOs).</li>
<li>Rework of Niching (NichePSO) to be more sane.</li>
<li>Removed the &#8220;games&#8221; package due to its unmaintained state. It will be
revised in a future release.</li>
<li>Removed several methods that are largely not required (in Meansurements
and other related classes)</li>
<li>FunctionMinimizationProblem and FunctionMaximizationProblem have been
removed. Instead, use FunctionOptimizationProblem with a given
Objective. The only valid Objectives are Minimize and Maximize, with
Minimize being assumed to be the default, if none is specified.</li>
<li>Added Lambda-Gamma neural networks</li>
<li>Removed a number of interal classes in favor of those already provided
by dependencies</li>
<li>A number of crossover strategies have had fixes applied / newly added</li>
<li>Cascading neural networks</li>
<li>Migrated from maven to SBT as build system</li>
<li>Several deprecations have been removed</li>
<li>Additional benchmark functions have been included</li>
</ul>


<h3>Issues</h3>

<p>For bug reports or feature requests, please raise an issue
<a href="http://github.com/cilib/cilib/issues">here</a>.
Feel free to contact us via the
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!forum/cilib-user">user</a> or
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!forum/cilib-dev">development</a> mailing
lists. We are also available on the FreeNode IRC network in the channel <code>#cilib</code>.</p>

<h3>Distribution</h3>

<p>In this release, we have changed the layout of the project such that there are now
two sub-projects: <code>library</code> and <code>simulator</code>. The <code>library</code> contains all the source
related to the algorithm components with the <code>simulator</code> containing the actual framework
to run the CIlib simulator application.</p>

<p>Additionally, the library will be available from the
<a href="http://search.maven.org/#artifactdetails%7Cnet.cilib%7Clibrary_2.9.2%7C0.7.5%7Cjar">Maven central</a>
repository for direct inclusion into your projects. This should result in friendlier usage
for all build tools in the current ecosystem (Maven, Ant, Gradle, SBT, etc).
The simulator assembly, which
contains the simulator application with bundled library code and a series of
example XML files is available <a href="http://cilib.net/releases/cilib-simulator-0.7.5.zip">here</a>.
It is recommended that a script is setup, and placed on your <code>$PATH</code> to run the simulator.</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/3122738.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/bash

# This script expects a few environment variables:
# $JAVA_OPTS: This variable represents the options passed directly to the JVM
#             Consult the JVM man page for these options.
# $CILIB_ASSEMBLY: Path to the assembled simulator jar file, which includes
#                  the cilib library and other required libraries

java ${JAVA_OPTS} -jar ${CILIB_ASSEMBLY} $@
</code></pre></noscript></div>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Netbeans, CIlib and SBT]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/07/18/netbeans-cilib-and-sbt/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/07/18/netbeans-cilib-and-sbt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a step-by-step guide to using Netbeans as your IDE for developing CIlib.
It is assumed that SBT 0.11.3, Scala 2.9.1 or later, and Netbeans 7.1 are installed
and that the latest CIlib source code has been retrieved.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Step 1: Get the Netbeans Scala plugin</h3>

<p>The nb-scala plugin is needed for Netbeans to work with Scala and SBT projects.
The following steps will install nb-scala:</p>

<ul>
<li>Download the correct version from <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/erlybird/files/nb-scala/">here</a></li>
<li>Extract the compressed archive somewhere on your hard drive (remember the location)</li>
<li>In Netbeans click on <code>Tools</code> -> <code>Plugins</code></li>
<li>At the top, click on the <code>Downloaded</code> tab</li>
<li>Click the <code>Add Plugins...</code> button near the top</li>
<li>Browse to the location (the one you had to remember) where the archive was extracted</li>
<li>Select all the modules (Ctrl-click does the trick)</li>
<li>Click the <code>Ok</code> button at the bottom</li>
<li>Click the <code>Install</code> button near the bottom of the <code>Plugins</code> window</li>
<li>Click <code>Next</code>, tick the <code>Accept</code> (only if you agree to the license) block then click <code>Update</code></li>
<li>If a validation warning appears it should be safe to click <code>Continue</code></li>
<li>At this point Netbeans will ask you to restart the IDE&#8230; please do so</li>
</ul>


<h3>Step 2: Get the sbt-netbeans plugin</h3>

<p>The sbt-netbeans plugin allows SBT projects wo be opened by Netbeans by generating
an Ant project using SBT commands. The following steps will install sbt-netbeans</p>

<ul>
<li>Open the global SBT plugins file usually situated at <code>~/.sbt/plugins/plugins.sbt</code>
(<code>~</code> is your home folder). If it does not exist create it.</li>
<li>Add the following to the end of the file

<pre><code>  resolvers += ScalaToolsSnapshots

  resolvers += "remeniuk repo" at "http://remeniuk.github.com/maven"

  libraryDependencies += "org.netbeans" %% "sbt-netbeans-plugin" % "0.1.4"
</code></pre>

<p>  Note the empty lines between each line of text.</p></li>
<li>Save the file</li>
</ul>


<h3>Step 3: Set up the project</h3>

<p>The following should be done in the terminal:</p>

<ul>
<li>Change to the directory CIlib is in, e.g. if it is in <code>~/src/cilib</code> then

<pre><code>  $ cd ~/src/cilib
</code></pre></li>
<li>Run SBT

<pre><code>  $ sbt
</code></pre></li>
<li>Run the netbeans command

<pre><code>  &gt; netbeans
</code></pre></li>
<li>Exit SBT

<pre><code>  &gt; exit
</code></pre></li>
</ul>


<h3>Step 4: Open the project in Netbeans</h3>

<p>CIlib should now be ready to be opened by Netbeans.</p>

<ul>
<li>Open Netbeans</li>
<li>Click <code>File</code> -> <code>Open Project...</code></li>
<li>Browse to the location that the CIlib folder is in e.g. if the CIlib source code
is in <code>~/src/cilib</code> then browse to <code>~/src</code>. The CIlib folder should have an icon
containing two red marks to the left of it.</li>
<li>Select the CIlib folder and click <code>Open Project</code> near the bottom</li>
<li>In the <code>Projects</code> view expand the cilib project and the <code>Libraries</code> folder</li>
<li>Open the <code>cilib-library</code> and <code>simulator</code> sub-projects by double clicking on them</li>
</ul>


<p>All the library code (algorithms, problems, etc) is in the <code>cilib-library</code> sub-project.</p>

<h4>Done</h4>

<p>Please report any errors found either on the CIlib github page or on IRC. If
there are people in the channel but are not responding leave a message anyway,
someone will eventually see it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New packaging, usage and removal of simulator scripts]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/07/16/removal-of-simulator-scripts/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-16T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/07/16/removal-of-simulator-scripts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the past, CIlib was released as a distribution and included a few artifacts:</p>

<ul>
<li>That actual CIlib &#8220;fat&#8221; jar file (together with external dependencies).</li>
<li>A collection of sample XML documents that defined the specifications for the XML based simulator.</li>
<li>Shell scripts for users to &#8220;run&#8221; the simulator, providing a XML specification.</li>
</ul>


<p>We are continuously trying to improve CIlib and, as such, we have decided to remove the simulator
scripts in favor of letting the simulator provide the &#8220;running&#8221; functionality in the form of an executable jar
file.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>Furthermore, from a source level, CIlib uses Maven as the project build tool but the fact that the project
wants to move to a Scala DSL replacement of the XML based simulator means that we should reevaluate the
use of Maven as well.</p>

<p>We will discuss each of these in the sections that follow.</p>

<h3>Maven, the unfriendly build tool</h3>

<p>The changes mentioned above require us to rethink how we package CIlib. It was decided
to rather split out the &#8220;simulator project&#8221; from the library. The remaining library is
now focused on all the algorithms and is devoid of the simulator logic.</p>

<p>Going forward, maven will be dropped and will be replaced with
<a href="http://www.scala-sbt.org">SBT</a>. SBT is a much simpler, more powerful build system,
particularly since the way you configure SBT is using scala and the SBT DSL. This means that
much of the maven plugin XML verbosity is simply removed and replaced with a few lines
of code - an infinitely saner way of doing the build definition.</p>

<h3>Simulator scripts removed, yes that&#8217;s right</h3>

<p>Going forward, we will be providing a simple reference from which users can create
their own &#8220;simulator&#8221; scripts, but this script will not be provided as part of the
CIlib distribution.</p>

<p>The script is available from the gist below, and is essentially for reference
purposes only (however we encourage the submission of any &#8220;fixes&#8221; that you may have):</p>

<div><script src='https://gist.github.com/3122738.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/bash

# This script expects a few environment variables:
# $JAVA_OPTS: This variable represents the options passed directly to the JVM
#             Consult the JVM man page for these options.
# $CILIB_ASSEMBLY: Path to the assembled simulator jar file, which includes
#                  the cilib library and other required libraries

java ${JAVA_OPTS} -jar ${CILIB_ASSEMBLY} $@
</code></pre></noscript></div>


<p>The gist provides a script that is friendly for Linux and Mac users - if any Windows
users require such a script, please either provide us with one or request that one is
created for you (not sure when we can get the time to figure that beast out though :P)</p>

<p>It is recommended that you place the script somewhere on your <code>$PATH</code>, so that it will be available
when needed. Please refer to the script itself for the specific variables that can be altered.</p>

<p>For any questions, please use the <a href="mailto:cilib-user@groups.google.com">mailing list</a>
or contact one of us in the <code>#cilib</code> on Freenode.net</p>

<p>Just in case, the information above will also be available in the documentation,
available from the links above.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Math formulae in documentation]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/07/13/math-formulae-in-documentation/"/>
    <updated>2012-07-13T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/07/13/math-formulae-in-documentation</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This has been something that has provided an unending amount of frustration: creating LaTeX style math
formula on the web. That being said, I&#8217;m very thankful to <code>oscarvarto</code> on the IRC channel for pointing us
towards a little library called <a href="http://www.mathjax.org/" title="MathJax">MathJax</a>.</p>

<p>We will be using this to produce proper documentation for math formulae. I believe that this is
a good step forward for our CIlib documentation effort. As a teaser of the formulae that will
be available, the standard PSO velocity update equation is given below (this includes the
inertia component):</p>

<p>$$v<em>{ij}(t+1) = w_i v</em>{ij}(t) + r_1 c_1 (y<em>{ij}(t) - x</em>{ij}(t)) + r_2 c_2 (\hat{y}<em>{j}(t) - x</em>{ij}(t))$$</p>

<p>This should provide us with better tools going forward :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Niching Makeover: part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/04/23/niching-makeover-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-23T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/04/23/niching-makeover-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The niching package has recently had a major refactor. This post and a few later
ones will explain the changes and how to use them.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Going Functional</h3>

<p>A functional approach has been taken with regards to the refactor. This means that
instead of objects being changed in place (e.g. <code>particle.setCandidateSolution(newSolution)</code>)
functions are used to create new objects with the changes in place. Currently CIlib
is not completely set up for this so to emulate it first clone the object then make
the changes to the cloned object.</p>

<p>The reason for taking a functional approach is to reduce mutable state. Mutable
state makes it harder to debug code because objects can be changed in multiple
places. Functional programs work with immutable data meaning that a copy of the
object is made when they need to be changed.</p>

<p>Functional programming is a different paradigm to the way the rest of CIlib is
implemented and so a few definitions are presented here to make the transition
easier. For those who want to make changes to the code a java library,
Functional Java (FJ), was used to implement the changes.</p>

<h3>Definitions</h3>

<ul>
<li><h4>Function:</h4>

<p>  A function is a unit of code that transforms an input into an output. The FJ
  library has a number of function classes for different numbers of inputs e.g.</p>

<pre><code>  F&lt;A, Z&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  is a function that takes an A as input and outputs a Z and</p>

<pre><code>  F2&lt;A, B, Z&gt;
  F3&lt;A, B, C, Z&gt;
  ...
  F8&lt;A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H, Z&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  take in an <code>A ... H</code> and return a <code>Z</code>. To apply the functions a method, <code>f(...)</code>,
  is called. Here is an example that takes a particle and returns its candidate
  solution.</p>

<pre><code>  F&lt;Particle, Vector&gt; solution = new F&lt;Particle, Vector&gt;() {
      public Vector f(Particle p) {
          return (Vector) p.getCandidateSolution();
      }
  }
</code></pre>

<p>  and to call it for a particular particle</p>

<pre><code>  solution.f(particularParticle)
</code></pre></li>
<li><h4>Tuple/Product:</h4>

<p>  A tuple is a collection of heterogeneous data. It allows functions to return
  more than one result. Using a similar naming convention to functions, FJ&#8217;s
  tuples are called</p>

<pre><code>  P1&lt;A&gt;
  P2&lt;A, B&gt;
  ...
  P8&lt;A, B, C, D, E, F, G, H&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>  To create a tuple use the static method <code>P.p(...)</code> e.g. to create a tuple of a
  particle with an associated score use</p>

<pre><code>  P2&lt;Particle, Double&gt; x = P.p(particle, score)
</code></pre>

<p>  To access the individual elements of a tuple use the <code>_n()</code> methods, where n
  is the position of the element in the tuple e.g.</p>

<pre><code>  Particle particle = x._1()
  Double score = x._2()
</code></pre></li>
<li><h4>Lists:</h4>

<p>  Lists in FJ have far more functionality (no pun intended) than Java&#8217;s collections.
  Here are a few operations that can be performed on them that apply the functional
  paradigm.</p>

<p>  &#8211; <strong>map</strong>: this applies a function to each element and returns a new list consisting
  of the output of the given function. e.g.</p>

<pre><code>  List&lt;Double&gt; numbers = List.list(-1.0, 0.0, 1.0);

  F&lt;Double, Boolean&gt; ltZero = new F&lt;Double, Boolean&gt;() {
      public Boolean f(Double p) {
          return p &lt; 0;
      }
  }

  List&lt;Boolean&gt; output = numbers.map(ltZero);
</code></pre>

<p>  The contents of <code>output</code> is <code>[false, false, true]</code></p>

<p>  &#8211; <strong>filter/removeAll</strong>: given a <code>List&lt;A&gt;</code>, <code>l</code>,  and a function <code>F&lt;A, Boolean&gt;</code>,
  <code>f</code>, <code>l.filter(f)</code> returns a list of all the elements in <code>l</code> which, when <code>f</code>
  is applied to the element, returns <code>true</code>. Similarly, <code>l.removeAll(f)</code>
  returns a list for which the result of <code>f</code> is <code>false</code>. Note that the input of
  the function, <code>A</code>, is the same type as the contents of the list.</p>

<p>  &#8211; <strong>foldLeft</strong>: given <code>List&lt;A&gt; l; F2&lt;B, A, B&gt; f; A a</code>, <code>l.foldLeft(f, a)</code>
  will apply <code>f</code> to <code>a</code> and the first element of <code>l</code> which results in a <code>B</code>.
  <code>f</code> is the applied to that result and the next element of <code>l</code> and so on until
  the list is exhausted. This operation is also known as reduce in other
  langueages/frameworks because it reduces a list of elements to one value.</p>

<p>  &#8211; <strong>head/tail</strong>: <code>head</code> returns the first element of the list and <code>tail</code> returns
  a new list containing every element except the <code>head</code> of the list. Similarly <code>last</code>
  returns the last element and <code>init</code> returns all but the last element of a list.</p></li>
</ul>


<h3>Functions</h3>

<p>In functional programming the user specifies what they want e.g. <code>list.filter(ltZero)</code>)
as opposed to how to get it e.g.</p>

<pre><code>for (Double n : numbers) {
    if (n &lt; 0) {
        newList.add(n);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Another thing is that functions can be composed, so the output of one function can
serve as the input for another function like the following</p>

<pre><code>F&lt;Algorithm, OptimisationSolution&gt; solution = new F&lt;Algorithm, OptimisationSolution&gt;() {
    public OptimisationSolution f(Algorithm a) {
        return a.getBestSolution();
    }
}

F&lt;OptimisationSolution, Boolean&gt; fitnessThreshold(final double threshold) {
    return new F&lt;OptimisationSolution, Boolean&gt;() {
        public Boolean f(OptimisationSolution s) {
            return s.getFitness().getValue() &lt; threshold;
        }
    };
}

List&lt;Algorithm&gt; algorithms = ...;
algorithms.filter(solution.andThen(fitnessThreshold(0.5)));
</code></pre>

<p>Here <code>solution</code> is composed with <code>fitnessThreshold</code>. An algorithm from the list
is passed to <code>solution</code> which returns an <code>OptimisationSolution</code> which gets passed
to <code>fitnessThreshold(0.5)</code> which determines if the solution is less than 0.5.
The result is a list of algorithms whose best solution is less than 0.5. If one
forgets most of their grammar rules it almost reads like English :)</p>

<p>One thing most people will notice is that the specification can get very verbose.
This is a consequence of using Java and its generics and not of functional
programming itself e.g. Scala can condense the above to one line per function.</p>

<h4>What&#8217;s next?</h4>

<p>In the next post the niching functions and structures will be introduced.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Simplified domain string grammar]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/04/17/simplified-domain-string-grammar/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-17T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/04/17/simplified-domain-string-grammar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>The need to change domain string grammar</h2>

<p>Defining a domain for use within a simulation is allowed within CIlib
as a simple string, such as:</p>

<pre><code>R(-10.0,3.0)^7,Z(0,1),B^2,R(0.0,5.0)
</code></pre>

<p>The notation is simple enough, but it is unfortunately difficult to work with
because the &#8216;,&#8217; token is overloaded to be both a separator for individual
dimensions within the domain definitions as well as being the separator for
lower and upper bound definitions within the dimension as well.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>In order to parse the above, a fair amount of state needs to be maintained
to know the current &#8220;scope&#8221;. This mutable state results is utter havoc with
concurrent usage of the domain parser. Two possible fixes could be applied to
resolve this issue:</p>

<ol>
<li>Re-create the parser each time, ensuring that each thread has its own
instance.</li>
<li>Make the parser stateless.</li>
</ol>


<p>Option (1) seems reasonable but has a massive amount of effort for very little
gain, whereas option (2) means that the parser can not only be reused, but that
the concurrency issues should just disappear because no state is mangled.</p>

<p>As a result, we have reimplemented the parser to be as stateless as possible.
There is still some state within the parboiled parser library code that we
have made peace with.</p>

<h2>What has changed</h2>

<p>The new parser now has two phases: (1) expansion and (2) transformation. The
expansion process is responsible to convert &#8220;exponent&#8221; strings into simpler
forms. As an example:</p>

<pre><code>R^7 =&gt; R,R,R,R,R,R,R
</code></pre>

<p>The transformation phase then converts the declared types into actual instances
that may be used within the algorithm. In order to differentiate the bounds
and dimension elements, the upper and lower bounds separator has been changed
from a &#8216;,&#8217; (comma) to a &#8216;:&#8217; (colon).</p>

<p>The new domain string is then:</p>

<pre><code>R(-10.0:3.0)^7,Z(0:1),B^2,R(0.0:5.0)
</code></pre>

<p>This is a minor change to the domain string representation, but the benefits
we have gained through this little modification are far too large to pass up.
To allow for the user to update the XML simulation specifications, clearer
error messages have been created with the simulation refusing to execute
without an updated domain string.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recent changes in master]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/04/12/recent-changes-in-master/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/04/12/recent-changes-in-master</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of patches recently made their way into the master branch of CIlib which
affect the way CIlib is used. The changes were made to the stopping conditions,
topologies and control parameters.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h3>Stopping Conditions</h3>

<p>In a bid to increase genericity (is that a word?) and remove duplicate code the
stopping conditions package was revamped. The new stopping condition classes are as
follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>MeasuredStoppingCondition which takes in a measurment an Objective and a target
The measurement is taken from the measurement package, objective can be either
Maximum or Minimum and target is the value the measurement must exceed (above
for Maximum, below for Minimum) for the algorithm to terminate.</p></li>
<li><p>MaintatinedStoppingCondition whcih takes in another StoppingCondition and the
number of consecutive iterations for which the condition must hold before the
algorithm can terminate.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Here are a few examples showing the differences from the before and after the
changes.</p>

<h4>Before</h4>

<p>Java:</p>

<pre><code>StoppingCondition sc = new MaximumIterations(2000);

StoppingCondition sc = new MinimumDiversity();
sc.setMinimumDiversity(ConstantControlParameter.of(0.01));
sc.setConsecutiveIterations(ConstantControlParameter.of(20));
</code></pre>

<p>XML:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;addStoppingCondition class="stoppingcondition.MaximumIterations" maximumIterations="2000"/&gt;

&lt;addStoppingCondition class="stoppingcondition.MinimumDiversity"&gt;
    &lt;minimumDiversity class="controlparameter.ConstantControlParameter" parameter="0.01"/&gt;
    &lt;consecutiveIterations class="controlparameter.ConstantControlParameter" parameter="20"/&gt;
&lt;/addStoppingCondition&gt;
</code></pre>

<h4>After</h4>

<p>Java:</p>

<pre><code>StoppingCondition sc = new MeasuredStoppingCondition(new Iterations(), new Maximum(), 2000);

StoppingCondition sc = new MaintainedStoppingCondition(new MeasuredStoppingCondition(new Diversity(), new Minimum(), 0.01), 20);
</code></pre>

<p>XML:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;addStoppingCondition class="stoppingcondition.MeasuredStoppingCondition" target="2000"&gt;
    &lt;measurement class="measurement.generic.Iterations"/&gt;
    &lt;objective class="stoppingcondition.Maximum/&gt;"
&lt;/addStoppingCondition&gt;

&lt;addStoppingCondition class="stoppingcondition.MaintainedStoppingCondition" consecutiveIterations="20"&gt;
    &lt;condition class="stoppingcondition.MeasuredStoppingCondition" target="0.01"&gt;
        &lt;measurement class="measurement.single.diversity.Diversity"/&gt;
        &lt;objective class="stoppingcondition.Minimum/&gt;"
    &lt;/condition&gt;
&lt;/addStoppingCondition&gt;
</code></pre>

<h3>Topologies</h3>

<p>The main difference regarding topologies is how to get the best entity/entities.
The getBestEntity method has been removed from the Topology classes and has been
placed in the Topologies class as a static method along with a number of other
methods. This was done to prevent overcrowding the topology interface and to
separate concerns since a topology is only suppose to impose a structure on a
population of entities.</p>

<h4>Before</h4>

<pre><code>Particle currentBest = topology.getBestEntity();
Particle gBest = topology.getBestEntity(new SocialBestFitnessComparator());

Particle nBest = particle.getNeighbourhoodBest();
// Although to the nBest could have changed so a more accurate way would be
// to iterate through the neighbourhood of the particle and compare each one
</code></pre>

<h4>After</h4>

<pre><code>Particle currentBest = Topologies.getBestEntity(topology);
Particle gBest = Topologies.getBestEntity(topology, new SocialBestFitnessComparator());

Particle currentNBest = Topologies.getNeighbourhoodBest(topology, particle);
Particle nBest = Topologies.getNeighbourhoodBest(topology, particle, new SocialBestFitnessComparator());
</code></pre>

<h3>Control Parameters</h3>

<p>Before, using control parameters that could change (e.g. linear increasing/decreasing
parameters) meant that the user had to update the parameters every iteration.
This became a hassle if a control parameter was introduced into code that already
had a big inheritance structure since a mechanism for updating the control parameters
would have to be introduced into each of those classes.</p>

<p>The changes made allow a control parameter to automatically update its value when
the getParameter method is called. One implication of this is that parameters cant
be updated only once per iteration. This is a problem for algorithms that use multiple
stopping conditions or whose stopping conditions dont include maximum iterations
(ControlParameters updateon percentage completion of an algorith which is determined
by the stopping conditions). This problem is dealt with by introducing a new
ControlParameter: UpdateOnIterationControlParameter which takes in a delegate
control parameter and updates it at the end of each iteration.</p>

<p>Additionally, some parameters were merged to avoid duplicating code and control
parameters are only bounded if used with BoundedControlParameter (which is a class
now, not an interface).</p>

<h4>Before</h4>

<p>Java:</p>

<pre><code>// Only updated at the end of an iteration or when updateParameter was called
LinearIncreasingControlParameter cp = new LinearIncreasingControlParameter();
cp.setUpperBound(0.9);
cp.setLowerBound(0.4);
cp.setParameter(0.4);

LinearDecreasingControlParameter cp = new LinearDecreasingControlParameter();
cp.setUpperBound(0.9);
cp.setLowerBound(0.4);
cp.setParameter(0.9);
</code></pre>

<p>XML:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;inertiaWeight class="controlparameter.LinearIncreasingControlParameter"&gt;
    &lt;upperBound value="0.9"/&gt;
    &lt;lowerBound value="0.4"/&gt;
    &lt;parameter value="0.4"/&gt;
&lt;/inertiaWeight&gt;

&lt;inertiaWeight class="controlparameter.LinearDecreasingControlParameter"&gt;
    &lt;upperBound value="0.9"/&gt;
    &lt;lowerBound value="0.4"/&gt;
    &lt;parameter value="0.9"/&gt;
&lt;/inertiaWeight&gt;
</code></pre>

<h4>After</h4>

<p>Java:</p>

<pre><code>// Updates whenever it is called
LinearlyVaryingControlParameter cp = new LinearlyVaryingControlParameter();
cp.setInitialValue(0.4);
cp.setFinalValue(0.9);

LinearlyVaryingControlParameter cp = new LinearlyVaryingControlParameter();
cp.setInitialValue(0.9);
cp.setFinalValue(0.4);

// Will update otherCP at the end of an iteration
UpdateOnIterationControlParameter cp = new UpdateOnIterationControlParameter();
cp.setDelegate(otherCP);

// Will always keep otherCP within bounds
BoundedControlParameter cp = new BoundedControlParameter();
cp.setBounds(new Bounds(-1, 1));
cp.setDelegate(otherCP);
</code></pre>

<p>XML:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;inertiaWeight class="controlparameter.LinearlyVaryingControlParameter" initialValue="0.4" finalValue="0.9"/&gt;

&lt;inertiaWeight class="controlparameter.LinearlyVaryingControlParameter" initialValue="0.9" finalValue="0.4"/&gt;

&lt;inertiaWeight class="controlparameter.UpdateOnIterationControlParameter"&gt;
    &lt;delegate class="controlparameter.LinearlyVaryingControlParameter" initialValue="0.9" finalValue="0.4"/&gt;
&lt;/inertiaWeight&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>If there are any questions join us on <a href="http://webchat.freenode.net/?channels=cilib">irc chat</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
