<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: announcements | Computational Intelligence Library]]></title>
  <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/categories/announcements/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cilib.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-19T08:42:04+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://cilib.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[CIRG]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CIlib 0.7.5 released]]></title>
    <link href="http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/075-release/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-12T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://cilib.github.com/blog/2012/11/12/075-release</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The 0.7.5 release of CIlib has been staged. The release consists of many changes from
various contributors. We would like to thank everyone for the contributions to this
release. What follows are the main highlights for the 0.7.5 release.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h3 id="change-log">Change Log</h3>
<p>Numerous changes have been included into the release, but the most notable are listed here:</p>

<ul>
  <li>New clustering implementation (for PSOs).</li>
  <li>Rework of Niching (NichePSO) to be more sane.</li>
  <li>Removed the “games” package due to its unmaintained state. It will be
revised in a future release.</li>
  <li>Removed several methods that are largely not required (in Meansurements
and other related classes)</li>
  <li>FunctionMinimizationProblem and FunctionMaximizationProblem have been
removed. Instead, use FunctionOptimizationProblem with a given
Objective. The only valid Objectives are Minimize and Maximize, with
Minimize being assumed to be the default, if none is specified.</li>
  <li>Added Lambda-Gamma neural networks</li>
  <li>Removed a number of interal classes in favor of those already provided
by dependencies</li>
  <li>A number of crossover strategies have had fixes applied / newly added</li>
  <li>Cascading neural networks</li>
  <li>Migrated from maven to SBT as build system</li>
  <li>Several deprecations have been removed</li>
  <li>Additional benchmark functions have been included</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="issues">Issues</h3>
<p>For bug reports or feature requests, please raise an issue
<a href="http://github.com/cilib/cilib/issues">here</a>.
Feel free to contact us via the
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!forum/cilib-user">user</a> or
<a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/?fromgroups=#!forum/cilib-dev">development</a> mailing
lists. We are also available on the FreeNode IRC network in the channel <code>#cilib</code>.</p>

<h3 id="distribution">Distribution</h3>

<p>In this release, we have changed the layout of the project such that there are now
two sub-projects: <code>library</code> and <code>simulator</code>. The <code>library</code> contains all the source
related to the algorithm components with the <code>simulator</code> containing the actual framework
to run the CIlib simulator application.</p>

<p>Additionally, the library will be available from the
<a href="http://search.maven.org/#artifactdetails%7Cnet.cilib%7Clibrary_2.9.2%7C0.7.5%7Cjar">Maven central</a>
repository for direct inclusion into your projects. This should result in friendlier usage
for all build tools in the current ecosystem (Maven, Ant, Gradle, SBT, etc).
The simulator assembly, which
contains the simulator application with bundled library code and a series of
example XML files is available <a href="http://cilib.net/releases/cilib-simulator-0.7.5.zip">here</a>.
It is recommended that a script is setup, and placed on your <code>$PATH</code> to run the simulator.</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/3122738.js?file='></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/bash

# This script expects a few environment variables:
# $JAVA_OPTS: This variable represents the options passed directly to the JVM
#             Consult the JVM man page for these options.
# $CILIB_ASSEMBLY: Path to the assembled simulator jar file, which includes
#                  the cilib library and other required libraries

java ${JAVA_OPTS} -jar ${CILIB_ASSEMBLY} $@
</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
